Guide to the New-York Historical Society Original Building Planning & Construction Records 1848-1946 NYHS-RG 3
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
- Series IV. Central Park West Construction: Expansion, 1925-1946; 68.48 Linear feet
  - Subseries IV.C. Plans and Drawings, 1925, 1935-1938; 60.73 Linear feet in many oversize folders, 2 flat boxes, 3 document boxes, and 5 rolls of blueprints
    - Walker & Gillette, 1937-1938 (Drawer 12A-B4, Folder 5)
      Includes 19 blueprints of plans of plaster work at new opening and elsewhere, corridor and hall details, list of rooms where plaster coves are required, design for floor in passenger & book stack elevator, bronze lettering, and other details (plan # 50, 51, 52, 53, 54, 55.Rev, 56, 57, 58, and 59).
    - Walker & Gillette, 1938 (Drawer 12A-B4, Folder 6)
      Includes 20 blueprints of plans for a telephone booth, wood molding under the skylights and elsewhere, changes in niches in the rotunda, a bronze panel in the rotunda and other bronze work, steel sash and glass brick, and color scheme for elevator car 1 (plan # 60, 61, 62, 63, 64, 65, 66, and 67).
    - Walker & Gillette, 1938 (Drawer 12A-B4, Folder 7)
      Includes 11 blueprints of plans of details in the east corridor and elsewhere, detail for the 77th Street vestibule, elevations of changes in assembly hall, alterations and marble & mosaic in the Old New York Room, and detail of street wall for property adjoining N-YHS (plan # 70 and 70A (these replace plan 51), 71, 73, 74, and 75).
    - Walker & Gillette, 1937-1938 (Drawer 9B-B4, Folder 6)
      Includes ten blueprints of plans for ornamental iron stairs, freight elevator door, bucks and loading platform, full scale details of pilasters for 76th and 77th Street elevators, main cornice detail, and granite detail in base course and elsewhere (plan # 101, 102, 102A, 103, and 104).
    - Walker & Gillette, 1937-1938 (Drawer 12A-B4, Folder 8)
      Includes 12 blueprints of plans of details of elevator dials, register grilles, brick window sills, granite thresholds, jamb and sills of elevators, bronze windows, plaster ornament, and exit light (plan # 105, 106, 109, 112, 116, and 117).
    - Walker & Gillette, 1937-1938 (Drawer 9B-B4, Folder 7)
      Includes 13 blueprints of plans of details (some full scale) of bronze entrance doors on 77th Street, windows, Views of Old New York Room, marble work, rotunda to assembly hall door, bronze inscription tablet dedicating the wings to the Thompsons (whose bequest was used to fund the expansion), and bulletin board (plan # 107, 110, 111, 113, 114, 115, and 115A).
    - Walker & Gillette, 1937 (Drawer 12A-B4, Folder 9)
      Includes seven whiteprints (linens) of electric work (plan # E.01, E.1, E.2, E.2m, E.3, E.4, E.5-2).
    - Walker & Gillette, 1937 (Drawer 12A-B4, Folder 10)
      Includes five whiteprints of plans concerning electric work (plan # E.01, E.1, E.2m, E.3, and E.4).
    - Walker & Gillette, 1937-1938 (Drawer 12A-B4, Folder 11)
      Includes 33 blueprints of plans concerning electric work (plan # E.01, E.1, E.2, E.2m, E.3, E.3 supplement, portion of E.3 Rev, E.4, E.5-2, E.6-1 (from MacNutt, Watts & Tankard), E-7, and one unidentified number of a riser diagram).
    - Walker & Gillette, 1938 (Drawer 12A-B4, Folder 12)
      Includes ten plans of electric work on tracing paper (plan # E.01, E.1, E.2, E.2m, E.3, E.3 supplement, E.4, E.5-2, E-7, and one unidentified number of a riser diagram).
    - Walker & Gillette, 1937 (Drawer 12A-B5, Folder 1)
      Includes six linen whiteprints, stamped "record drawing," of plans concerning heating & ventilating (plan # H&V.1, H&V.2, H&V.3, H&V.4, H&V.5, and H&V.6).
    - Walker & Gillette, 1937-1938 (Drawer 12A-B5, Folder 2)
      Includes six linen whiteprints of plans concerning heating & ventilating (plan # H&V.1, H&V.2, H&V.3, H&V.4, H&V.5, and H&V.6).
    - Walker & Gillette, 1937-1938 (Drawer 12A-B5, Folder 3)
      Includes 21 whiteprints of plans concerning heating & ventilating (plan # H&V.1, H&V.2, H&V.3, H&V.4, H&V.5, and H&V.6).
    - Walker & Gillette, 1937-1938 (Drawer 12A-B5, Folder 4)
      Includes 25 blueprints of plans concerning heating & ventilating (plan # H&V.1, H&V.2, H&V.3, H&V.4, H&V.5, and H&V.6).
    - Walker & Gillette, 1937 (Drawer 12A-B5, Folder 5)
      Includes eleven blueprints of plans concerning plumbing, drainage and standpipes (plan # P.1, P.2, P.4, P.5, and unnumbered).
    - [Walker & Gillette?], 1937 (Drawer 12A-B5, Folder 6)
      Includes 21 blueprints of plans concerning plumbing and drainage. One is Walker & Gillette's plan # P.4. The creators of the other plans are unidentified.
    - Walker & Gillette, 1937 (Drawer 12A-B5, Folder 7)
      Includes four plans on tracing paper concerning plumbing and drainage (plan # P.1, P.2, P.4, and P.5).
    - Walker & Gillette, 1937 (Drawer 12A-B5, Folder 8)
      Includes 11 blueprints and one reproduction of framing and foundation plans (plan # S.2, S.3, S.4, S.5, S.6, S.7, S.8, S.9, S.10, S.12, and S.13). The blueprints are linen, stamped as the inspector's official copy.
    - Walker & Gillette, 1937 (Drawer 12A-B5, Folder 9)
      Includes 21 blueprints of framing and foundation plans (plan # S.1, S.2, S.3, S.4, S.5, S.6, S.7, S.8, S.9, S.10, and S.13).
    - Walker & Gillette, 1936-1937 (Drawer 12A-B5, Folder 10)
      Includes plans on tracing paper: three related to the book stacks (plan #17a, 20, and one unnumbered); an unnumbered elevation from 1936 of the original building; plans related to granite, cornices, ornamental iron, bronze, pilasters, and other matters (plan # 101, 102, 102a, 103, 104, 105, 106, 107, 108, 109, 110, 111, 112, 113, 114, 115a, and 117); sketches related to granite, marble, metal grilles, and a lighting panel (sketch # SK.100, SK.101, SK.102, SK.103, and SK.104); and lighting fixture designs (design # 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 7a, 7b, 9, 10, 11, 14, 16, 17, 17a, and one unnumbered).
    - Walker & Gillette, 1937? (Drawer 12A-B5, Folder 11)
      Includes five blueprints: two sketches concerning granite (SK.100 and SK.101) and three unnumbered plans concerning bronze doors and vestibules.
    - Walker & Gillette, 1938 (Drawer 12A-B5, Folder 12)
      Includes various fragmented blueprints of plans concerning lighting strips, doors, toilets, electric panels, and heating & ventilating.
    - Walker & Gillette. Reproductions, 1937-1938 (Drawer 12A-B4, Folder 13)
      Includes eight Mylar(?) reproductions of elevations (plan # 8, 9, 10, and 11).
    - Walker & Gillette. Reproductions, 1937-1938 (Drawer 12A-B4, Folder 14)
      Includes four Mylar(?) reproductions of elevations (plan # 8, 9, 10, and 11).
    - Walker & Gillette. Reproductions, 1937 (Drawer 12A-B4, Folder 15)
      Includes five reproductions (reduced size) of floor plans (plan # 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6).
    - Walker & Gillette. Reproductions, 1937-1938 (Drawer 12A-B4, Folder 16)
      Includes four reproductions of elevations (plan # 8, 9, 10, and 11).
    - Walker & Gillette. Reproductions, 1937-1938 (Drawer 12A-B4, Folder 17)
      Includes eleven reproductions of elevations (plan # 8, 9, 10, and 11).
    - Walker & Gillette. Reproductions, 1937 (Drawer 12A-B4, Folder 18)
      Includes five reproductions of elevations, details of existing stonework, and exterior details and wall sections (plan # 8, 9, 10, 15, and 16).
    - Walker & Gillette. Reproductions, 1937-1938 (Drawer 12A-B4, Folder 19)
      Includes four reproductions wth backward images of elevations (plan # 8, 9, 10, and 11).
    - Walker & Gillette. Reproductions, 1937? (Drawer 12A-B4, Folder 20)
      Includes reproductions of various plans. Negative images, unnumbered.
    - Walker & Gillette. Folded Plans (1 of 16), 1936-1938 (Box 29, Folder 1)
      This set of 16 folders includes folded (unflattened) blueprints. They can be used only with assistance from the Public Services staff. This folder includes six blueprints concerning stonework, book stack, corridors, interior court elevations, and wall treatment: # 15, 17a (1936), 18, 19, 20a, and 25.
    - Walker & Gillette. Folded Plans (2 of 16), 1937 (Box 29, Folder 2)
      Includes five blueprints concerning elevations of grilles and sash, elevation of new entrance on 77th Street, details of stairs, and Executive Committee room: # 26, 27, 28, 29, and 30.
    - Walker & Gillette. Folded Plans (3 of 16), 1937-1938 (Box 29, Folder 3)
      Includes seven blueprints concerning corridors, grilles, air outlets, details of kitchen and various rooms, partitions, and sleeves in wall: # 31, 32, 33, 34, 35, 37, and 38.
    - Walker & Gillette. Folded Plans (4 of 16), 1937 (Box 29, Folder 4)
      Includes four blueprints concerning elevations & schedules of doors, door trims and frames, paneling in the Director's room, and the Views of Old New York gallery: # 40, 41, 47, and 48.
    - Walker & Gillette. Folded Plans (5 of 16), 1937-1938 (Box 29, Folder 5)
      Includes the blueprint of the Specification Schedule of Material, # 49 (5 sheets).
    - Walker & Gillette. Folded Plans (6 of 16), 1937-1938 (Box 29, Folder 6)
      Includes six blueprints concerning plaster work, corridors and stair hall, floor design for the elevators, bronze lettering in 77th Street doorway, push bars for vestibule doors, and window enclosures: # 50, 51, 52, 55.Rev, 56, 57, 58, and 59.
    - Walker & Gillette. Folded Plans (7 of 16), 1938 (Box 29, Folder 7)
      Includes eight blueprints concerning color scheme for elevator #1, changes to niches, wood molding, telephone booth, changes in floor levels, details of steel sash and glass brick, bronze plaque in rotunda floor, and bronze doors and frame: # 60, 61, 62, 63, 64, 65, 66, and 67.
    - Walker & Gillette. Folded Plans (8 of 16), 1938 (Box 29, Folder 8)
      Includes eight blueprints concerning bronze doors, corridors, 77th Street vestibule, Assembly Hall changes, marble and mosaic floors, detail of street wall for property adjoining N-YHS, and layout for garden walls on 76th Street: # 68, 70, 70a, 71, 73, 74, 75, and 76.
    - Walker & Gillette. Folded Plans (9 of 16), 1937 (Box 29, Folder 9)
      Includes two blueprints concerning granite details: # 101 and 102.
    - Walker & Gillette. Folded Plans (10 of 16), 1937 (Box 30, Folder 1)
      Includes three blueprints concerning cornice details, pilasters, and ornamental iron: # 102a, 103, and 104.
    - Walker & Gillette. Folded Plans (11 of 16), 1937 (Box 30, Folder 2)
      Includes four blueprints concerning jamb and sills, bronze entrance doors, brick window sills, granite thresholds, and 2nd floor windows: # 106, 107, 109, and 110.
    - Walker & Gillette. Folded Plans (12 of 16), 1937-1938 (Box 30, Folder 3)
      Includes four blueprints concerning details of Views of Old New York gallery, dials for elevators, marble work, and door from rotunda to Assembly Hall: # 111, 112, 113, and 114.
    - Walker & Gillette. Folded Plans (13 of 16), 1938 (Box 30, Folder 4)
      Includes three blueprints concerning bronze inscription tablet (full size), bulletin board, and plaster ornament and exit light: # 115, 115a, and 117.
    - Walker & Gillette. Folded Plans (14 of 16), 1937 (Box 30, Folder 5)
      Includes seven blueline whiteprints of electric work: # E.01 (basement), E.1 (1st floor), E.2 (2nd floor), E.2m (2nd floor mezz), E.3 (3rd floor), E.4 (roof), and E.5-2 (book stack).
    - Walker & Gillette. Folded Plans (15 of 16), 1937 (Box 30, Folder 6)
      Includes eight blueprints concerning framing, typical floor and roof slabs, and various alterations: # S.3, S.4, S.5, S.8, S.10, S.11, S.12, and S.13.
    - Walker & Gillette. Folded Plans (16 of 16), 1937 (Box 30, Folder 7)
      Includes ten blueprints of sketches concerning book stacks, roof openings, doors, granite, Kalamein details, and other matter: # SK.100, SK.101, SK.102, SK.104, and unnumbered.
    - Walker & Gillette. Rolled Plans (1 of 7), 1937-1938 (Roll 1, Folder -)
      In addition to the above plans, there are 6 rolls of Walker & Gillette blueprints. These rolled plans are duplicates or earlier versions of the plans found above. Following are the plan numbers in this roll. The date shown is the latest date found above the title block on the plan (i.e., latest of revised or issued date). Plan # 5A.flap (12/27/37), 9 (6/24/37), 10 (10/7/37), 11 (6/24/37), 12A.flap (12/27/37), 13A.flap (6/24/37), 13P3 (6/24/37), 13P3 (9/9/37), 14 (2 copies, both 9/9/37), 18 (2/11/38), 19 (6/24/37), 19A (6/24/37), 22 (9/9/37), 38 (7/8/37), and 44 (9/16/37).
    - Walker & Gillette. Rolled Plans (2 of 7), 1937-1938 (Roll 2, Folder -)
      Includes plan # 2 (7/29/37), 3 (6/24/37), 4 (12/27/37), 5 (6/24/37), 5 (12/27/37), 6 (2 copies of 9/9/37), 6 (3/8/38), 6a (9/9/37), 6a (3/8/38), 7 (2 copies of 9/9/37), 7 (10/9/37), and 7 (3/8/38).
    - Walker & Gillette. Rolled Plans (3 of 7), 1937-1938 (Roll 3, Folder -)
      Includes plan # 27 (6/24/37), 31 (8/11/37), 31(12/10/37), 32 (2 copies of 7/9/37), 32 (12/10/37), 33 (2 copies of 7/9/37), 33 (12/10/37), 35 (7/8/37), 40 (9/24/37), 43 (2 copies of 9/23/37), 51 (1/17/38; voided and replaced by 70 & 70A); 57 (1/21/38), and 114 (1/26/38).
    - Walker & Gillette. Rolled Plans (4 of 7), 1937-1938 (Roll 4, Folder -)
      Includes plan # 23 (6/2/37), 23 (2 copies of 7/2/37), 24 (6/2/37), E.01 (5/5/37), E.01 (4/4/38), E.1 (5/2/38), E.1 (6/1/38), E.2 (4/4/38), E.2m (4/4/38), E.4 (2/9/38), H&V 2 (4/12/37), H&V 5 (4/12/37), and H&V 6 (4/12/37).
    - Walker & Gillette. Rolled Plans (5 of 7), 1937-1938 (Roll 5, Folder -)
      Includes plan # 30 (9/2/37), 30 (9/9/37), 47 (9/27/37), 48 (12/31/37), 102A (7/16/37), 103 (5/7/37), 104 (5/24/37), 110 (10/11/37), 110 (12/27/37), 111 (12/27/37), 115 (3/22/37), and 115A (5/18/38).
    - Walker & Gillette. Rolled Plans (6 of 7), 1937-1938 (Roll 6, Folder -)
      Includes three sets (5 sheets each) of the Specification Schedule of Material (drawing 49): Sheet 1 (11/26/37), Sheet 2 (11/26/37), Sheet 3 (11/26/37), Sheet 4 (11/26/37), and Sheet 5 (12/29/37).
    - Walker & Gillette. Rolled Plans (7 of 7), 1937-1938 (Roll 7, Folder -)
      Includes plan # 101 (4/21/37) and 102 (5/7/37). (This roll also includes General Bronze plan # 3.)
    - Westinghouse Electric & Manufacturing, 1937-1938 (Drawer 7A-B13, Folder 20)
      Includes three whiteprints of controller diagrams.
    - Westinghouse Electric Elevator Co. (Chicago), 1937 (Drawer 7A-B13, Folder 21)
      Includes 3 Westinghouse blueprints concerning elevators, stamped approved by Walker & Gillette. Also includes Walker & Gillette's related plan #106 (details of jamb & sills of passenger elevator #1 and stack elevator #3).
    - Westinghouse Electric Elevator Co. (Chicago). Folded Plans, 1937 (Box 30, Folder 8)
      Includes four blueprints concerning elevators, stamped approved by Walker & Gillette.
    - William Somerville, Inc. (New York), 1938 (Drawer 12A-B6, Folder 6)
      Includes eight blueprints of detail & schedule of wood doors and details for the director's room and Executive Committee room.
    - York & Sawyer, 1925 (Drawer 12A-B1, Folder 22)
      Includes eight blueprints of floor plans proposed by York & Sawyer in 1925 for the expansion.
    - York & Sawyer, 1935-1936 (Drawer 12A-B2, Folder 1)
      Includes ten sets of blueprints of York & Sawyer's proposals updated to 1935 for the expansion. Most of the sets are identical.
    - Unidentified (1 of 2), 1937? (Drawer 12A-B, Folder 2)
      This folder and the next include two sets of sketches on kraft paper of floor plans and other matter.
    - Unidentified (2 of 2), 1937? (Drawer 12A-B6, Folder 3)
    - Unidentified, [1937?] (Drawer 12A-B6, Folder 4)
      Includes two sets of photographic reproductions of schematic floor plans showing the planned purposes of the various spaces in the building.
    - Unidentified, [1938?] (Drawer 12A-B6, Folder 1)
      Includes one hand drawn schematic on kraft paper of a plan for a library table. The creator of the plan is unidentified.
  - Subseries IV.D. Post-Construction Plans, 1940, 1945-1946, undated; 1.3 Linear feet in six oversize folders.
    Related Archival Materials Note
    Correspondence with Philip Youtz related to his plans can be found in the General Correspondence record group (NYHS-RG 2).
    The subseries is arranged in chronological order.
    The Post-Construction Plans subseries includes a small number of plans from the 1940s, the period of time shortly after the completion of the expansion of the Central Park West building in the late 1930s. Most of the subseries includes preliminary blueprints from 1945-1946 developed by Philip N. Youtz concerning a further expansion of the N-YHS building along West 76th Street; these plans were unrealized. The subseries also includes a blueprint prepared by N-YHS engineer Garrett H. Winter of the boiler and engine room (1940) and a set of schematic floor plans, possibly from the 1940s.
    - Boiler and Engine Room, 1940 (Drawer 12A-B2, Folder 5)
      Includes five blueprints prepared by engineer Garrett H. Winter.
    - Education Building, 1945 (Drawer 12A-B2, Folder 8)
      Includes multiple sets of Philip Youtz's preliminary blueprints for an expansion of N-YHS to include an Education Building.
    - Layout Plans, 1946 (Drawer 9B-B5, Folder 1)
      Includes Philip N. Youtz's preliminary plan for a 76th Street expansion of the N-YHS building.
    - Layout Plans, 1946 (Drawer 9B-B5, Folder 2)
    - Layout Plans, 1946 (Drawer 12A-B2, Folder 7)
      Includes reproductions of Philip N. Youtz's preliminary plan for a 76th Street expansion of the N-YHS building.
    - Unidentified Set of Floor Plans, 1940s? (Drawer 12A-B2, Folder 4)
      Includes a set of schematic floor plans.